<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vertue of the coffee drink. First publiquely made and sold in England, by Pasqua Rosee.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670-1680?</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V646B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.2[372]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99887003</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99887003</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181693</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06461)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181693)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A1:1[375])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vertue of the coffee drink. First publiquely made and sold in England, by Pasqua Rosee.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: damaged with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Coffee --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:181693:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <head>The Vertue of the <hi>COFFEE</hi> Drink. Firſt publiquely made and ſold in England, by <hi>Paſqua Roſee.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Grain or Berry called <hi>Coffee,</hi> groweth upon little Trees, only in the <hi>Deſerts of Arabia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is brought from thence, and drunk generally throughout all the Grand Seigniors Dominions.</p>
            <p>It is a ſimple innocent thing, compoſed into a Drink, by being dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in an Oven, and ground to Powder, and boiled up with Spring wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and about half a pint of it to be drunk, faſting an hour before, and not Eating an hour after, and to be taken as hot as poſsibly can be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured; the which will never fetch the skin off the mouth, or raiſe any Bliſters, by reaſon of that Heat.</p>
            <p>The Turks drink at meals and other times, is uſually <hi>Water,</hi> and their Dyet conſiſts much of <hi>Fruit;</hi> the <hi>Crudities</hi> whereof are very much corrected by this Drink.</p>
            <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>ality of this Drink is cold and Dry; and though it be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> neither <hi>heats,</hi> nor <hi>inflames</hi> more then <hi>hot Poſſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th the Orifice of the Stomack, and fortifies the heat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> good to help digeſtion and therefore of great uſe to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a Clock a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the morning.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>ens the <hi>Sprits,</hi> and makes the Heart <hi>Lightſome.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fore Eys, and the better if you hold your Head <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Steem that way.</p>
            <p>It ſuppreſſeth Fumes exceedingly, and therefore good againſt the <hi>Head-ach,</hi> and will very much ſtop any <hi>Defluxion of Rheums,</hi> that diſtil from the <hi>Head</hi> upon the <hi>Stomach,</hi> and ſo prevent and help <hi>Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> and the <hi>Cough of the Lungs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is excellent to prevent and cure the <hi>Dropſy, Goat,</hi> and <hi>Scurvy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is known by experience to be better then any other Drying Drink for <hi>People in years,</hi> or <hi>Children</hi> that have any <hi>running humors</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, as the <hi>Kings Evil.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It is very good to prevent <hi>Miſ-carryings in Child-bearing Women.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a moſt excellent Remedy againſt the <hi>Spleen, Hypocondriack Winds,</hi> or the like.</p>
            <p>It will prevent <hi>Drowſineſs,</hi> and make one fit for buſines, if one have occaſion to <hi>Watch;</hi> and therefore you are not to Drink of it <hi>after Supper,</hi> unleſs you intend to be <hi>watchful,</hi> for it will hinder ſleep for 3 or 4 hours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is obſerved that in Turkey, where this is generally drunk, that they are not trobled with the Stone, Gout, Dropſie, or Scurvey, and that their Skins are exceeding cleer and white.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is neither <hi>Laxative</hi> nor <hi>Reſtringent.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Made and Sold in St. <hi>Michaels Alley</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> by <hi>Paſqua Roſee,</hi> at the Signe of his own Head.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
